Guide to the Ramón Gómez de la Serna Papers [Guía a los materiales de Ramón Gómez de la Serna], 1906-1967 SC.1967.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Writings [Escritos], II.
  - Essays and Articles [Ensayos y artículos], 3.
    - Buenos Aires
      - "Misterios de Buenos Aires" (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - "Calles especializadas" — "La gran calle Florida" (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - "Replica de los botánicos—El botánico aquí" (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - "Hay que regar las calles" (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - "Piano de remate" (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - "Buenos Aires" (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - "Tormenta de Santa Rosa" (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - "Plaza Miserere" (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - "Bodrio" (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - "Avenida de mayo" (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Loose Notes (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - "Temario: 'Bancos de flores'": Manuscripts and Clippings (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - "Buenos Aires: plano general" (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - "Recuerdo de Keyserling" (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - "Corrientes, Florida y la diagonal" (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - Loose Notes, Items 227-238 (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - "Esquelas que intercalar para tembladeral": Epitaphs (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - "La pampa" (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - "El porvenir" (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - "Prólogo a Explicación de Buenos Aires de Ramón Gómez de la Serna" (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - "Yo he sido un gordo y me ha ido bien con esa figura maciza y ancha" (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Unidentified Fragments about Buenos Aires (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Unidentified Fragments about Buenos Aires (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Manuscript Fragments about "El frio en Buenos Aires" and "La barriguita" (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Manuscript Fragment (Dialog) (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Published Clippings by Ramón and Others (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Romanticismo
      Gathered here are documents, graphic materials, clippings of Ramón's own articles on the subject, and 23 large manuscript sheets (numbered 2-26, with 6 and 7 missing). The latter are probably lecture notes defending a romantic way of life and repeating what is said in the first chapter to the Carolina Coronado biography.
      Aquí se reúnen documentos, materiales gráficos, recortes de los propios artículos de Ramón sobre el tema y 23 hojas de manuscritos grandes (numeradas del 2 al 26, con 6 y 7 faltantes). Estas últimas son probablemente apuntes de presentaciones que defienden una forma de vida romántica y repiten lo que se dice en el primer capítulo de la biografía de Carolina Coronado.
      - "Romanticismo Español": Book and Newspaper Clippings (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - "Cosas mias publicadas": Manuscript Pages and Published Clippings (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - "Romanticos Catalanes": Manuscript Pages and Published Clippings (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - "Romanticismo": Manuscript Fragment (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - "Romanticismo": Notes (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - "Romanticismo": Notes and Clippings (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - "Poetas menores del Romanticismo: Francisco Zea, Ros de Olano, Tertulia María Nodier, Tasara, Garcia Gutierrez, Menéndez Valdés" (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - "Grafica Romanticismo": Clippings of Images (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - "Romanticismo y armas al hombre" by Adriano de Valle: Article Clipping (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - "Historia universal romanticismo": Article Clippings (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - "Cosas periodistícas Romanticismo": Article Clippings (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - "Archivado Espronceda": Article Clippings and Some Notes on José de Espronceda (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - "La Avellaneda": Article Clippings on Gertrudis Gómez de Avellaneda (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - "Romanticismo americano": Article Clippings (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - "Archivado Cadalso": Article Clippings on José Cadalso (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - "José Zorrilla": Article Clippings on José Zorrilla (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - "Duque de Rivas": Article Clippings on Duque de Rivas (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - "Carolina Coronado": Article Clippings on Carolina Coronado, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - "Romanticismo": Notes and Article Clippings on Romanticism (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - "Fígaro" (Mariano José de Larra): Article Clippings, Notes, and Manuscript Drafts (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - "Don Miguel de Mañara": Article Clippings and Notes (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - "Don Juan": Article Clippings and Some Notes (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - "Don Juan": Article Clippings (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - "Don Juan de Zorrilla": Article Clippings and Some Notes (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - "Grafica Don Juan": Image Clippings of Don Miguel de Mañara (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Editores
      This section comprises Ramón's loose notes expressing a repetitive and almost obsessive tirade against publishers for their immoral exploitation of the writer.
      Esta sección comprende las notas sueltas de Ramón que expresan una diatriba repetitiva y casi obsesiva contra los editores por su explotación inmoral del escritor.
      - Original Cover of Notes "Editores" (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Loose Notes, Items 1-89 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Loose Notes, Items 90-185 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Loose Notes, Items 186-287 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Temas diferentes
      As its title indicates, this section holds notes for Ramón's newspaper articles dealing with a variety of subjects including prehistoric animals, subway bars, 'genocide' as opposed to genocide, the immodesty of women bathers, modern youth, capitalism and the perversion of money, clocks, allergies, modern sculpture, bells, butterflies, teddy bears, Russians and the moon, animal skulls symbolizing America, frying pans and cookery, and—more voluminously—on frogs and toads, and 'Sunday'. Included are also manuscript drafts on a variety of topics, such as the minute forms of life found in the encyclopedia and on unmarked handkerchiefs. Notes on any one subject may be the result of an accumulation over a period of ten years or more.
      Como su título lo indica, esta sección contiene notas para los artículos periodísticos de Ramón que tratan sobre una variedad de temas que incluyen animales prehistóricos, bares del metro, 'genocidio' en oposición al genocidio, la inmodestia de las mujeres bañistas, la juventud moderna, el capitalismo y la perversión del dinero, relojes, alergias, esculturas modernas, campanas, mariposas, osos de peluche, rusos y la luna, cráneos de animales que simbolizan América, sartenes y cocina y, más voluminosamente, en ranas y sapos, y "domingo". También se incluyen borradores de manuscritos sobre una variedad de temas, como las formas de vida diminutas que se encuentran en la enciclopedia y en pañuelos sin marcar. Las notas sobre cualquier tema pueden ser el resultado de una acumulación durante un período de diez años o más.
      - "Lo cursi": Notes and Clippings (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - "Invencía/Mocedad Mocerío" (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Loose Notes (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - "Barlovento y virazón" (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - "El balduque y el brulote" (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Loose Notes (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - "El genocidio" (Box 15, Folder 17)
      - "Claro de la luna" (Box 15, Folder 18)
      - Loose Notes (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - "Azafrán y pimientón" (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - "Sartenes" (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Loose Notes and Clippings (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - "Bares del subterráneo" (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Loose Notes (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - "Saurios" (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - "Diccionario" (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - "Relojes y tiempo" (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - "Ranas y sapos" (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - "Esqueleto campo" (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - "Esqueletos en el campo" (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - "El dinero" (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - "Barbas" (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - "Humorismo" (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - "Tallarines" (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - "Alegría" (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - "Domingo" (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - "Arboles: Cultura del plátano" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Afilador" (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - "Mariposas" (Box 16, Folder 21)
      - "El fotógrafo" (Box 16, Folder 22)
      - "Los rusos y la luna" (Box 16, Folder 23)
      - "Osos de los niños" (Box 16, Folder 24)
      - "Las haches y el la y el le" (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - Loose Notes (Box 16, Folder 26)
      - "Cosas oro," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - "Escultores," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 28)
      - "Esqueletos del campo," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 29)
      - "Los fotógrafos artísticos," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - "Multitud en las cornisas," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 31)
      - "Osos," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 32)
      - "Pañuelos sin marcar," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 33)
      - "Predilección por los ositos," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 34)
      - "Radiolarios, espongiarios y otros más," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 35)
      - "Los saurios y las noches sauricas," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 36)
      - "Trajes baño," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 37)
      - Untitled (Related to "Radiolarios"), Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 38)
      - "Dias de Chimenea," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 39)
      - "El matador de Guisando," Typescript (Box 16, Folder 40)
      - "En la ciudad desproporcionada," Manuscript (Box 16, Folder 41)
      - Clippings of Published Articles by Ramón and Others (Box 16, Folder 42)
    - Sobre novela y novela corta y cuento
      The documents in this section consist of two fragments of typescript, four annotated clippings, and over a hundred manuscript notes. They contain ideas either not included in or—the majority—subsequent to the publication of the essay "Novelismo" in Ismoa (2nd ed. Buenos Aires, 1947), reflecting Ramón's conception of the novel and short story.
      Los documentos en esta sección consisten en dos fragmentos de mecanografía, cuatro recortes anotados y más de cien notas manuscritas. Contienen ideas no incluidas en o –en su mayoría– posteriores a la publicación del ensayo "Novelismo" en Ismoa (2ª ed. Buenos Aires, 1947), que reflejan la concepción de Ramón de la novela y el cuento.
      - Original Cover of Material (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Transcription of Selected Items (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - "Novela/Ideas sobre la novela" (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - "La novela" (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - "Notas para una nueva novela" (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - "Sobre la novela" (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - "La novela" (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - "El cuento" (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Caprichos y fantasmagorías
      Ramón describes the caprice (caprichos) represented here in subheadings as surreal, absurd, humorous, and terrifying. Most of them are in form of brief notes; others are longer pieces on manuscript pages. Apparently, some of the caprichos were originally intended for inclusion in the novel "El hombre perdido."
      Ramón describe los caprichos representados aquí en subtítulos como surrealistas, absurdos, humorísticos y terroríficos. La mayoría de ellos están en forma de notas breves; otros son piezas más largas en páginas manuscritas. Aparentemente, algunos de los caprichos fueron originalmente destinados a ser incluidos en la novela "El hombre perdido".
      - "Caprichos" (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - "Un pelo volante" (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - "Caprichos para España" (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - "Muy surrealistas y absurdistas" (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - "Terríficos" (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - "Diálogo de las tazas" and "Aerolandia," Manuscripts (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - "Caprichos," Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - "Caprichos surrealistas," Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - "El elefante cleptomano," Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - "El que borró el crimen," Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - "El órgano carcelario," Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Ballet—Antropofagia
      Documents in this section comprise impressions and ideas on night clubs, modern and classical ballet, exhibiting an attitude of puritanical censure towards the promiscuous, venal sexual behaviors of the modern city, expressed through the wit and humor of metaphor.
      Los documentos en esta sección comprenden impresiones e ideas sobre clubes nocturnos, ballet moderno y clásico exhibiendo una actitud de censura puritana hacia los comportamientos sexuales promiscuos y banales de la ciudad moderna, expresados a través del ingenio y el humor de la metáfora.
      - "Cabaret," Notes (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - "Ballet—Antropofagia," Notes (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Corrigiendo retratos
      This section contains revised notes, drafts, and published clippings concerning some of Ramón's biographical sketches of several individuals, including Colette, Francisco Villaespesa, Manuel Machado, and Pío Baroja.
      Esta sección contiene notas revisadas, borradores y recortes publicados sobre algunos de los bocetos biográficos hechos por Ramón sobre varias personas incluyendo a Colette, Francisco Villaespesa, Manuel Machado y Pío Baroja.
      - Loose Notes and Clippings (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - "Baroja y Villaespesa," Manuscript (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - "Manuel Machado," Typescript (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - "Oración para el poeta," Typescript (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - "Colette," Clipping (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Unidentified Title ("Colette"), Clipping (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified Title ("Baroja"), Clipping (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified Title ("Prólogo corrigiendo"), Clipping (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Futuros ensayos
      Ramón's mostly handwritten notes in this section reveal critical commentaries on the modern world: the corruptive and false illusion of the cinema exposing the secret aspirations of society; the truck as an image for the machine culture as well as the revolutionary violence of the workers; airplanes and cars and a modern obsession with speed and travel divert man from his true spiritual nature; banks ought to modify their structure in order to end exploitation.
      En esta sección, las notas de Ramón, escritas principalmente a mano, revelan comentarios críticos sobre el mundo moderno: la ilusión corrupta y falsa del cine que expone las aspiraciones secretas de la sociedad; el camión como imagen de la cultura de la máquina, así como la violencia revolucionaria de los trabajadores; aviones y automóviles y una obsesión moderna con la velocidad y los viajes desvían al hombre de su verdadera naturaleza espiritual; los bancos deberían modificar su estructura para terminar con la explotación.
      - "Cine" (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - "Cultura del camión" (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - "Autos—Velocidad—Turismo" (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - "Avión" (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - "El león" (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - "Bancos" (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - "Icaza" (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - "El eco" (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Cartas a las golondrinas
      Featured here are phrases and fragments for one or more uncompleted "Cartas a las golondrinas." They have apparently been partly transcribed and arranged by Luisa Sofovich to create a posthumous letter to the swallows.
      Aquí se presentan frases y fragmentos para una o más incompletas "Cartas a las golondrinas". Aparentemente, Luisa Sofovich parcialmente las transcribió y las organizó para crear una carta póstuma a las golondrinas.
      - "Carta golondrinas," Loose Notes (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - "Carta póstuma a las golondrinas," Annotated Typescript (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - "Cartas al las golondrinas," Published Clipping (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - "Prólogos"
      In these notes, Ramón recorded ideas on aesthetics and artistic reality in general, commenting on his own work and lamenting the social realism of the post-war Spanish generation.
      En estas notas, Ramón registró ideas sobre la estética y la realidad artística en general, comentando su propio trabajo y lamentando el realismo social de la generación española de la posguerra.
      - "Realismo" (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - "Estética literaria" (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - "Ultima Estética" (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Unidentified Typescript, Fragment (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - "La literatura," Fragment (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Tiempo y reloj
      This section comprises notes, fragments, and clippings that are discussing the topics of time and time-keeping.
      Esta sección comprende notas, fragmentos y recortes que discuten los temas de tiempo y cronometraje.
      - Tiempo y reloj (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Revés del circo
      The documents in this folder include impressions of the circus, especially with regard to clowns and elephants. There are hints at investigating the mysterious, perhaps Freudian, side of the circus.
      Los documentos en esta carpeta incluyen impresiones del circo, especialmente con respecto a payasos y elefantes. Hay indicios de investigar el lado misterioso, quizás froidiano del circo.
      - Revés del circo (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Rupestre, Barroco, Renacimiento
      Comprised here are Ramón's definitions and descriptions of the Baroque, considering it in a larger historical perspective as a peculiar Spanish religious phenomenon. In the Renaissance section, Ramón claims that Spain's Catholicism defended the country from the paganism of that period and from the austerity of the Reformation. He argues that the baroque period was more inspired by the prospect of the New World than by a counter movement to the Reformation. In other folders, one can find an article condemning communist–inspired murals, some ideas on paintings in general, and on Spanish cave paintings in particular. Most of the material here can be dated to the 1940s and reveals Ramón's desire to study the myth of the 'eternal Spain'. Some manuscripts are drafts for radio talks and may also have been published in the press.
      Aquí se incluyen las definiciones y descripciones de Ramón sobre el barroco, considerándolo en una perspectiva histórica más amplia como un fenómeno religioso español peculiar. En la sección del Renacimiento, Ramón afirma que el catolicismo español defendió al país del paganismo de ese período y de la austeridad de la Reforma. Argumenta que el período barroco se inspiró más en la perspectiva del Nuevo Mundo que en un movimiento contrario a la Reforma. En otras carpetas, se puede encontrar un artículo que condena los murales de inspiración comunista, algunas ideas sobre pinturas en general y sobre pinturas rupestres españolas en particular. La mayor parte del material aquí puede datarse de la década de 1940 y revela el deseo de Ramón de estudiar el mito de la "España eterna". Algunos manuscritos son borradores para charlas de radio y también pueden haber sido publicados en la prensa.
      - "Barroco—Renacimiento" (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - "Lo rupestre" (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - "Cuevas de España" (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - "Pintura" (Fragment) (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - "Pintura mural" (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - "Rococó—Renacimiento" (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - "Bodas de América y España" (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - "El renacimiento": Radio Script, 1940 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - España
      This section includes memories and impressions of Madrid during the Monarchy and Ramón's childhood. Present are also notes on Calderón, Quixote, Jorge Manrique, Lope de Vega, an article on the history of Madrid and on the town Paredes de Nava, birthplace of Jorge Manrique, Pedro Berruguete, and General San Martín. A large part of the documents consists of three manuscript articles. "Repetición de España" is about the eternal, unchanging character of the country, with its spiritual wealth despite, or rather because of, its poverty and sobriety. The second, "Perspectiva de España," deals with the author's sense of mission of seeing Spain from a true perspective, an idealized one, and describing it to South America. He sees the new nationalist Spain as the eternal Spain, which has been saved and rejuvenated, displaying an almost ingenuous faith in the truth of his vision. The third article, "Castilla antes del milenio," discusses the historic Castile, which he exalts as representing the central essence of Spain.
      Esta sección incluye recuerdos e impresiones de Madrid durante la Monarquía y la infancia de Ramón. También hay notas sobre Calderón, Quijote, Jorge Manrique, Lope de Vega, un artículo sobre la historia de Madrid y sobre el pueblo Paredes de Nava, lugar de nacimiento de Jorge Manrique, Pedro Berruguete y el general San Martín. Una gran parte de los documentos consta de tres artículos manuscritos. "Repetición de España" trata sobre el carácter eterno e inmutable del país, con su riqueza espiritual a pesar de, o más bien debido a, su pobreza y sobriedad. La segunda, "Perspectiva de España", trata del sentido de misión del autor de ver a España desde una perspectiva verdadera, idealizada, y describirla a Sudamérica. Él ve a la nueva España nacionalista como la España eterna, que se ha salvado y rejuvenecido, mostrando una fe casi ingenua en la verdad de su visión. El tercer artículo, "Castilla antes del milenio", trata sobre la Castilla histórica, que él exalta como representación de la esencia central de España.
      - "Madrid" (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - "España e Hispano-Americanismo" (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - "Perspectiva de España" (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - "Repetición de España" (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - "El surgente Madrid" (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - "Castilla antes del milenio" (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - "Cante jondo" (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - "Calderón" (Box 23, Folder 8)
      - About Spanish Art, Radioscript Fragment (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - About Spanish Art, Manuscript Fragment (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - "Paredes de Nava, Jorge Manrique, Los Berruguete y el General San Martín" (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - "Lope" (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - "Pedro de Mena" (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Published Clippings (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Bio, España, política, archivar, ida y vuelta a España, 1949
      This is a compilation of political notes reflecting Ramón's views on the Second Republic, the civil war, his 1949 visit to Spain, and his political ideas in general. They provide further context for his declared allegiance to Franco, a fact he did not discuss in "Automoribundia". He looks back with nostalgia to the relative calm of the monarchy, without sympathy for the Republic and its disorders, whose causes he attributes primarily to the socialist and communist movements. Apart from Franco, the only politicians referred to are Republicans, and all are subjected to bitter, scathing criticism: Álvarez del Vayo, Juan Negrín y López, Araguistaín, Manuel Azaña, and Indalecio Prieto. Ramón favored the establishment of a Catholic military dictatorship to prevent a communist revolution and to maintain stability at all costs. His journey to Madrid in 1949 appears to not have been the success he had hoped for because his impressions are far from enthusiastic, and he seems to have returned embittered to Buenos Aires. Later notes commenting on the contemporary world—reference is made to the Polaris missile—reveal a feeling of increasing isolation and despair at the world.